大家好 我是《天天太空人》的Tim Dodd
Hi, it's me, Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
液体燃料火箭发动机的工作原理是将燃料和氧化剂
Liquid fueled rocket engines operate by flowing fuel and oxidizer into a combustion chamber
以极高压力注入燃烧室
at ridiculously high pressures,
从而将尽可能多的物质以尽可能快的速度向后抛出
in order to throw as much mass out the flaming end of the rocket as quickly,
也就是达到尽可能高的效率
and thereby as efficiently as possible.
那发动机是如何达到工作状态的?
But how does it get that way?
到底要如何 或者更难的情况 在天上要如何
How on earth, and even more difficultly, how off earth
让发动机达到运行的压力与温度?
do you get an engine up to operating pressures and temperatures?
发动机通常需要泵来驱动 而泵的动力又来自发动机的运行
Engines often utilize pumps which themselves rely on the engine to be running in order to get power.
而"拥有一台运行的发动机"
And having a rocket engine run
和"让一台发动机开始运行" 完全是两码事
and getting a rocket engine running are two wildly different things.
让泵 阀门 温度和压力都完美地达到工作条件 简直就是在刀尖上跳舞
There is often an extremely delicate dance to get the pumps, valves, temperatures, and pressures
all up to operating conditions perfectly.
有时哪怕几毫秒的偏差
Get it wrong by just a few milliseconds even,
都可能引起爆炸 摧毁整台发动机
and you can cause a detonation that can completely destroy the engine.
因此 我们今天将要深入探讨火箭发动机的启动方法
So today we're going to do a deep dive on how exactly you start a rocket engine.
尽量讲得全一点 从简单的固体火箭发动机
We'll cover pretty much everything from a simple solid rocket motor
到错综复杂的液体火箭发动机
to all of the intricacies of liquid fueled rocket engines,
内容涵盖发动机热环境管理 起转
including thermally conditioning the engine, the spin up process,
惊心动魄的瞬态过程 和燃料的点火方式
the scary transient regions, and the actual ignition of the propellants.
还会探讨其他难点 比如如何在太空启动发动机
Then we'll talk about some of the extra challenges like starting a rocket engine in space,
然后我们将一步一步探索
and then we're going to actually go step by step
一台发动机启动时内部的情况
inside a rocket engine during its startup.
本期视频有一点长
Now this is a very long video,
以上是各部分时间戳
so here's the time stamps for each section,
也可以点击下方的时间戳跳转
and we've got the YouTube timeline broken up into those sections too.
如果你更喜欢阅读文章
还可以前往下方链接查看文章版
And if you're more of a reader, we've got you covered with an article version up
里面参考链接都有标注
at everydayastronaut.com with links and sources.
那么咱们开始吧!
That being said, let's get started.
开始之前
Right up front,
av723951018
我强烈建议大家先观看《火箭发动机冷却方法介绍》
I need to suggest that you watch my videos "Why don't rocket engines melt?"
与《火箭发动机循环方式介绍》这两期视频
and "How to power a rocket engine".
av300259217
本期视频中很多概念都在这两期视频中有所提及
As those videos will help with a lot of concepts that we talk about in this video.
相信我 没看过的话先去看那两期吧
Trust me, don't even try to watch this video without having watched those
打好基础很重要
because they lay a lot of vital groundwork.
在开始前的最后 我还有一些好消息
And lastly, before we get started, I've got some great news.
我们这款超高细节1:100猎鹰九号火箭模型终于补货了
Our highly detailed one 100 scale metal Falcon 9 rocket models are finally back in stock.
欢迎前往下方链接购买
Get them while you can everydayastronaut.com/shop.
好 相信大家已经了解液体火箭发动机工作原理背后的基础知识
Okay, assuming you have all the basic knowledge of how a liquid fueled rocket engine works,
我们先从最简单的火箭发动机讲起 固体火箭发动机
let's actually start off with the most simple rocket engine to start, a solid rocket motor.
到目前为止 启动最简单的火箭就是固推了
By far, the easiest rocket to start has to be a solid rocket motor.
实际上可能大伙自己都亲身经历过
In fact, there's actually a good chance that you've done this yourself.
如果你们发射过火箭模型 或者放过鞭炮
If you've ever launched a model rocket or even fireworks,
那你基本已经完全掌握了固体火箭发动机的启动程序了
you've already pretty much experienced the ignition sequence of a solid rocket motor.
固体火箭的燃料 顾名思义
Solid rocket propellant is exactly what it sounds like it.
火箭的燃料就是固体
A solid that is rocket propellant.
通常就是预先将氧化剂和燃料混合好的药柱
It's usually like a sludge of pre-mixed fuel and oxidizer,
只需一点能量就能开始燃烧
and all it takes is energy to get the combustion process started.
对于小型模型火箭的发动机
In the case of a small model rocket motor,
能量通常来自于引线的热量
that energy usually comes from the heat from a set of small wires.
大一点的固体火箭通常需要更多的能量才能启动
Bigger solid rocket motors will usually require more energy to get started,
所以有时会使用黑火药
so sometimes they'll have some black powder,
就是一种火药 通过引信点燃
which is basically gun powder, that will initially ignite from the wires,
通过连锁反应点燃固体燃料
and then a chain reaction will occur that will then light the solid propellant
之后的燃烧是自我维持的
where it will continue to self sustain.
但对于使用大型固推的入轨级火箭来说
But once you start talking about large orbital class solid rocket boosters
比如航天飞机
like those on the Space Shuttle,
或者阿尔忒弥斯计划的主力火箭 太空发射系统(SLS)
or maybe those on the Space Launch System, otherwise known as the SLS rocket,
which is at the heart of the Artemis program,
它们的固推在顶部有一个类似炸弹的东西 用来启动点火流程
there's basically a bomb sitting on top of the booster that starts the ignition process.
上面有一个装置叫NASA标准雷管(NSD)
There's a device called a NASA Standard Detonator or an NSD,
它从双子座计划时就开始使用
and this is a little device used since the Gemini program
Frangible nut用于航天飞机起飞时释放固推
用于各种分离动作 比如助推器分离 抛整流罩 爆炸螺母
for things like separation events on booster separation and fairings and frangible bolts or
而在今天所讲的 NSD用于触发固推内的燃烧反应
in this case, they're the device that they actually use to start the chain of reactions
从而让庞大的固体火箭点火运行
that'll get these massive solid rocket boosters going.
在点火时 指令会发送给不止一个NSD
When it's go time, a signal is sent to not just one NSD,
而是一整套带冗余的NSD 保证固推顺利点火
but a completely redundant NSD to ensure the boosters light.
毕竟万一有一个哑火了就出大事了
After all, if one doesn't light, it would be very, very bad.
另外别忘了 固推一旦点火 就不可能再关机了
And don't forget, once you light a solid rocket booster, there is no shutting it down.
NSD会先炸穿一层很薄的密封
The NSDs burst through a thin barrier seal,
然后引燃烟火传爆药
which then lights a pyrotechnic booster charge.
传爆药点燃 点火器启动器 内的燃料
Then that booster charge is what ignites propellant inside an igniter initiator,
然后点燃 固推主启动器
which then lights the main booster igniter,
最终点燃整个固推内部的装药 这一切都在一瞬间发生
and that lights the entire surface of the core of the booster, virtually simultaneously.
简单总结下来
So for a little overview here,
就是固推内至上而下发生的一连串爆炸反应
it's basically a waterfall of explosives that cascade down from the top of the booster
最终在电光火石之间点燃了整个固推
until eventually the entire booster is lit, pretty much all at once.
小炸药音引爆中型炸药 然后引爆大型炸药 最后固推点火
Basically stepping up from a small charge, to a medium charge, to a large charge, to booster ignition.
就像我刚说的 基本就是在固推顶部引燃了一个炸弹
Like I said, it's basically more or less a bomb that's lit at the top of the booster or
或者说是固推前段启动了点火程序
otherwise known as the forward segment that starts the ignition process.
整体而言 就是这么简单
It's really just about that easy. That's kind of their whole point.
点火程序简便 结构简单 非常可靠
They're super simple and because of their easy ignition process, they're very reliable,
当然缺点也很明显 就是点火后无法关机
but they definitely have limitations such as not being able to be shut down,
固推的效率也不如液体火箭发动机高
and they aren't nearly as high performing as a liquid fueled rocket engine.
但液体火箭发动机的启动可远没有这么简单
But starting a liquid fueled rocket engine is just not anywhere near that easy.
有无数复杂的操作
There's a ton of steps you need to take,
而首先最重要的可能就是对发动机进行吹除
but perhaps the first and most important thing to do is to purge the engine
并调控其热环境 让它准备好面对即将到来的极端工况
and thermally condition it for the extreme environments it's about to encounter.
启动一台液体火箭发动机前
Before you get a liquid fueled rocket engine running,
要先让它准备好面对即将到来的极端温度环境
it has to be prepared for the ludicrous temperatures it's about to face.
而且我这里说的并不是极端的高温
And believe it or not, I'm not talking about the extreme heat.
而是极端的低温
I'm actually talking about the extreme cold.
多数入轨级火箭的发动机会让燃料流经发动机喷管内壁
Not only do most orbital liquid fueled rocket engines run propellant through the walls of the engine
从而防止燃烧室和喷管熔化
to keep the combustion chamber and nozzle from melting,
同时 泵的内部每秒也有数千升的低温燃料流过
but the pumps themselves will flow upwards of thousands of liters per second of cryogenic propellants,
而低温会让金属 阀门 轴承变脆 更容易发生故障
which can make the metals, valves and bearings brittle and failure prone.
这点适用于所有使用低温推进剂的发动机
This of course, is specifically true of any engine that uses cryogenic propellants,
即所有使用液氧的发动机
so any liquid oxygen, also known as LOX powered rocket engine,
尤其使用液氢或甲烷这些
燃料也是低温的发动机
and especially those that run on hydrogen or hydrolox
and methane or methylox for their fuels,
尤其使用液氢或甲烷这些
燃料也是低温的发动机
which are also cryogenic propellants.
这些燃料组合占了
入轨级火箭发动机里的大多数
These propellants all make up the majority of rocket engines
that we see on orbital rockets.
但在开始用推进剂冷却发动机之前
But before you even begin to chill down the engine with the propellants,
还需要吹除发动机内的空气和水汽
you need to purge the engine from moisture and air pockets,
这一步通常使用氮气
and this is usually done with nitrogen.
在低温燃料注入前 如果有水汽存在于管路内
If there's any water vapor in the lines before cryogens are introduced,
它们就会结冰 损坏发动机
it'll freeze and cause damage to the engine
可能造成孔穴堵塞 密封圈损坏 喷油器堵塞等等
with the potential for clogged orifices, damaged seals, clogged injectors, etc etc.
但对于氢氧发动机 由于液氢的温度太低了
But if it's a hydrolox engine, liquid hydrogen is so cold,
甚至能让氮气也变成一坨堵住的冰
it can even turn any residual nitrogen into a solid block of ice,
同样也会造成上述故障
and do all of the bad things we just mentioned.
而且这样的结冰堵塞很难发现
And an ice blockage can be really hard to investigate,
因为导致故障的罪魁祸首
because the evidence of the root cause of the failure
在等到工程师靠近调查的时候早已融化消失
melts away by the time a human can even get close enough to investigate.
因此 氢氧火箭发动机通常使用另一种惰性气体进行吹除——氦
Because of this, hydrogen powered rocket engines are usually purged with another inert fluid, helium.
氦是唯一熔点低于氢的物质
Helium is the only element that has a lower melting point than hydrogen.
所以即使有液氢在 它也不会结冰
So in the presence of liquid hydrogen, it won't freeze solid.
发动机的吹除与预冷可以在发射前几小时到几分钟内进行
Purging and chill down of the engines can be anywhere from a few hours before launch to a few minutes,
不同发动机进行的时间都不同
but this varies very much from engine to engine.
可以听听发射播报中"发动机预冷""发动机冷却"之类的口令
So listen for something like engine cool down or engine chill down, called out on comms...
一级发动机冷却开始
Stage one engine chill has started.
好的 我们已经听到"一级发动机冷却开始"的口令了
All right, there's that call that "Stage one engine chill has started".
当发动机的吹除作业完成后
Okay, so once the engine has been purged of moisture,
我们就可以开始使用低温燃料调控发动机的热环境了
we can start to actually thermally condition the engine with the cryogenic propellants.
这一流程首先开启一个叫"预阀"的阀门
This process involves opening what's known as a prevalve,
它是连接发动机与燃料箱的大阀门
which is the big valve that connects the engines to the propellant tanks.
推进剂随后填充泵 一路流到主阀
The propellant will fill the pumps and fill all the way down to the main valves,
主阀通常是燃料或氧化剂的一个或多个阀门
which is usually one or a number of valves for fuel and oxidizer.
这时 泵就已经浸泡在低温推进剂内了
Then the pumps will just soak in a bath of cryogenic propellant,
直到泵冷却到足够低的温度
until the pumps eventually get down to those frigid temperatures.
对于低温推进剂来说
In comparison to cryogenic propellants,
发动机之前的 对人类来说很舒适的常温环境其实是非常"烫手"的
the engine is actually scorching hot under normal, everyday human comfortable ambient temperatures.
哪怕把发动机拿到南极的特大暴风雪里
Even if an engine was hanging out in Antarctica during a deadly blizzard,
那个温度也能瞬间让低温推进剂沸腾
it would still pretty much immediately boil off any cryogenic propellant that touches it.
所以还需要管路把沸腾的推进剂排出
So there needs to be a vent line to remove the boiled off propellant.
氧气通常可以直接排放进大气中 几乎不会有风险
Oxygen can usually just be dumped overboard,
which poses little to no risk when being vented into the atmosphere.
但一般来讲 沸腾后气态的低温推进剂 比如甲烷或氢气
But in general, a cryogenic fuel that now has boiled off into a gas like methane or hydrogen
需要收集起来 要么重新降温输回火箭
needs to be recaptured and either chilled and pumped back into the rocket,
要么以可控的方式排出
or it can be vented away from the rocket in a controlled manner
比如使用火炬排放可以防止积累的可燃气体发生爆炸
where a flare can prevent a buildup from accidentally detonating.
因为如果随意将甲烷或氢气排放到大气中
Because if you just vent gaseous methane or hydrogen out into the atmosphere in an uncontrolled manner,
后果可能有一点点糟糕
don't expect very good things to happen.
因此 在航天飞机 SLS 德尔塔-4等火箭发射前会有这些火花
This is why you see those giant sparkler lit before Space Shuttle, SLS or Delta IV Heavy launches.
它们不是给发动机本身点火的
It's not to light the actual engines and start combustion,
而是为了在主燃烧室点火前消耗掉启动过程中从发动机逸出的大量氢气
it's to burn off the gassiest hydrogen that will exit the engine during the startup process
before main combustion chamber ignition.
称为"径向向外火花发生器"(ROFI)
These are called Radial Outward Firing Initiators or ROFIs.
用来防止氢气气团堆积并发生爆燃
They're just preventing a large cloud of hydrogen from gathering and potentially detonating,
你们懂的 后果可能很糟糕
which as you know, could be very, very bad.
但是 发动机冷却并不是仅仅为了保护自身不受低温影响
But the engine isn't chilled down just to protect the engine from the cold temperatures.
还要保护推进剂不受相对高温的发动机的影响
It's also to protect the propellant from the relatively warm engine,
哪怕推进剂在发动机启动前还是放在室温下的罐体内的
even when it's just resting at ambient temperatures before the engine is running.
如果推进剂在到达叶轮和泵之前就开始沸腾
If the propellant is beginning to boil before it reaches the impellers and the pumps,
会造成气蚀 说白了就是液体中有气泡
it can cause cavitation or basically bubbles in the liquid,
这些气泡会腐蚀泵 造成损毁
and those bubbles can actually chip away at the pumps and completely ruin them.
伊龙·马斯克在我们探讨猛禽发动机的泵的时候谈及过此事
Elon Musk talked about this a little bit when we were talking about the Raptor engines pumps.
要尽量避免气蚀 或者说空泡的产生
So what you're trying to avoid is cavitation or bubble generation.
如果流体内出现空泡
If you start generating bubbles,
这些空泡就会……一点点侵蚀泵的叶片
the bubbles will actually eat away at your blades.
听上去很神奇 气泡竟然会腐蚀金属 但就是这样
Like it's weird like bubbles would chip away metal, but they will.
而且如果气蚀严重 泵就变成泡泡机了
And, and if you cavitate too much then you're gonna just be a bubble generator
推进剂压力降低 发动机就熄火了
and you'll lose pressure and starve the engine.
另外 空泡除了会腐蚀泵的叶片
And not only can those bubbles chip away at the pumps,
还会造成泵超速
the bubbles can also cause the pumps to over speed,
导致发动机因推进剂供给不足而熄火
and or starve the engine of the propellant,
甚至可能让它变成理想混合比的燃烧
and potentially create stoichiometric conditions,
释放最大的能量 产生最高的温度
which is the most energetic and highest temperature conditions,
结果当然也是灾难性的
and of course, those can be catastrophic.
因此 让发动机冷却到工作温度是非常重要的
Getting an engine down to operating temperatures is absolutely vital,
为了保证发动机的正常运转 计算机会对其密切监控
and it's monitored very closely by the engine's computers that run the engine.
实际上 正是因为一台RS-25发动机在点火前没有冷却下来
In fact, it was a fear that one of the RS-25 wasn't cooling down prior to ignition,
才导致阿尔忒弥斯一号任务取消了2022年8月的首次发射尝试
that caused the first scrub of Artemis 1 on its very first launch attempt in August of 2022.
-推迟了  -官宣推迟了吗?  -官宣了  -好吧
-It's a scrub.  -It is officially a scrub?  -Officially.  -All right.
-发射指挥宣布了  -发射指挥宣布推迟本次发射
-Launch director called it.  -Launch director called a scrub.
三号发动机的温度传感器
Engine number three's temperature sensor
显示发动机没有冷却到所需温度
wasn't showing the engine had cooled down enough to the required temperatures,
因此当天的发射尝试取消
so the launch attempt was scrubbed for the day.
后来发现发动机可能已经冷却下来了
It turns out the engine was likely indeed at the right temperatures,
但是传感器本身出故障了
but the sensor itself was erroneous.
但这也体现了发动机预冷的重要性
But it just goes to show how important engine chill down is.
哪怕只有一台发动机没有冷却下来
If an engine's not cooling down as expected,
发射指挥也不会鲁莽下令起飞
no diligent launch conductor would proceed towards liftoff.
因为接触自燃燃料通常是剧毒的
所以使用这种燃料的发动机也叫"毒发"
一些液体火箭发动机不适用低温推进剂 比如接触自燃燃料
Some liquid fueled rocket engines don't use any cryogenic propellants, such as hypergolic propellants.
接触自燃燃料会在两种组元接触时立即发生燃烧
Hypergolic propellants are those that will spontaneously combust
when they come in contact with each other.
而这些燃料在室温下是很稳定的
But hypergolics are happy as a clam at room temperature,
因此 这些发动机并不需要预冷
and because of that, the engines don't really need to be chilled down.
实际上 很多洲际导弹可以加满燃料放上好几年 随时待命
In fact, many intercontinental ballistic missiles can sit for years fueled up and ready to go,
并且可以在很短时间内发射
and can be fired within a moment's notice.
美国有过几款接触自燃燃料的入轨级火箭发动机
There've been a handful of US-based hypergolic orbital rocket engines
比如大力神2号的LR-87发动机 德尔塔-2上面级的AJ-10发动机
such as the LR-87 used on the Titan II or the AJ-10 on the Delta II's upper stage.
而苏联研发了一大堆毒发
But the Soviet Union developed a ton of hypergolic rocket engines.
av294439869
感谢@天外飞舰
看过我那期《苏联火箭发动机家族史》视频的观众可能记得
For those of you who have watched my entire history of Soviet rocket engines video may know
苏联 尤其那位推进工程的传奇 瓦连京·格鲁什科 超级喜欢毒发
the Soviets, well, specifically propulsion engineering legend, Валенти́н Глушко́, loved hypergolic rockets.
看看画面中的发动机族谱就能发现
Just take a quick glance at this family tree that we put together.
下面那一堆黄色或橙色的发动机都是毒发
Any orange or yellow engine near the bottom of the chart is hypergolic.
真的是琳琅满目
Yeah, that's a lot of hypergolic rocket engines.
有些比较有名的 比如质子号火箭一级的RD-275
Some of the more noteworthy ones are the RD-275s on the first stage of the Proton rocket.
或者大名鼎鼎的RD-270 一款全流量分级燃烧循环发动机
Or the mighty RD-270, that was a full flow stage combustion cycle engine,
给登月的大火箭造的 可惜没上过天
designed for a massive lunar rocket, that sadly never left the drawing board.
好 我们已经冷却了发动机 或者选择了毒发
Okay, so we've chilled our engine down or we're using hypergolic,
发动机已经来到了运行温度
so we're already at operating temperatures,
现在该开始让泵转起来了
but now we need to get the pumps spinning,
该让它们达到数万千帕的工作压力 上千上万的转速了
and get them up to operating pressures of potentially hundreds of bar and tens of thousands of RPM.
或许火箭发动机的第一条定律 或许全宇宙都通用吧
Perhaps the number one rule with rocket engines, and I guess the universe in general,
就是流体总是从高压流向低压
is pressure always wants to flow from high pressure to low pressure.
因此发动机的上游需要有极高的压力
So engines need to have extremely high pressure upstream,
才能保证系统内不会发生"回火"
in order to not send a flame backwards through the system,
否则可能会带来严重后果
which would inevitably lead to a catastrophic failure.
大家应该已经知道 挤压式发动机结构相对简单
As you likely know, having a simple pressure fed engine is easy.
打开几个阀门 发动机就开始工作了
You just open some valves and ta da, you're running an engine.
推进剂贮存压力已经很高
The propellant is already stored at high pressure,
从而在运行压力下自行向燃烧室流动
so it'll naturally flow into the combustion chamber at the necessary operating pressures.
那拥有超高转速涡轮泵的入轨级火箭发动机呢?
But what about an orbital class rocket engine that has turbo pumps that spin at absurd speeds?
我们要讲的是高动力 高室压的发动机
We're talking high power, high chamber pressure engines.
观察图中正在运行的开式循环泵压火箭发动机
Take a look at an open cycle turbo pump powered rocket engine while it's running.
注意到燃料泵和氧化剂泵通过同一根轴连接到为它们供能的涡轮
Notice the fuel pump and the oxidizer pump are connected by a shaft to a turbine that powers them.
涡轮的功率超级大
Turbines can be insanely powerful,
有些发动机一个涡轮的功率就能达到数十万马力
with some engines making hundreds of thousands of horsepower from just a simple turbine.
那么涡轮的动力来自于哪里呢?
So what powers the turbine?
哪些动力实际来源是哪里?
Where does that power actually come from?
发动机内通常还有一个预燃室或某种形式的燃气发生器
Well, there's usually a preburner or a gas generator of some kind,
它某种程度上像是发动机的发动机
that's kind of like a rocket engine on its own right,
它的核心功能就是给涡轮供能
and it's sole purpose is to produce energy to power the turbine.
仔细观察图中的燃气发生器
But take a closer look at the gas generator.
它通过泵提供燃料
而泵的能量来自燃气发生器
It's fed by the pumps,
the pumps are powered by the gas generator,
但燃气发生器由泵提供燃料
但泵的能量来自燃气——
but the gas generator is fed by the pumps,
but the pumps are powered by the gas-
好了 你们懂了吧
Okay, yeah, you, you get the point!
这就是启动一台泵压式液体火箭发动机的第二个步骤 起转
Okay, here's the second step of starting a liquid pump fed rocket engine: spin up.
有很多方法能让泵达到所需转速
Now, there's a handful of ways you can actually get the pumps up to speed,
但是多数情况是使用额外的高压气体让泵起转
but perhaps the most common is by utilizing a separate high pressure gas to get the pumps spinning.
气体可以来自箭载系统上储存氦气的复合材料缠绕压力容器(COPV)
This can either be supplied with an onboard system like
helium stored in a high pressure COPV or Composite Overwrap Pressure Vessel,
也可以使用地面设备 不再受重量限制
or it could be supplied by ground systems where weight doesn't matter
因为它不会跟着火箭上天
since it doesn't contribute to the overall mass of the rocket.
两种方法都会把氦气或氮气泵入燃气发生器内
In either case, high pressure helium or nitrogen is pumped into the gas generator
让涡轮起转 达到运行转速
to get the turbine spinning up to operating speeds.
在很短时间内 发动机的泵相当于由冷气推进器驱动的
For a short period of time, the engine's pumps are being powered by basically a cold gas thruster,
效率并不高
which isn't very efficient.
冷气推进器比冲很低 即效率低
A cold gas thruster has a low specific impulse or a low efficiency,
而且你还希望它能在发动机独立运行前尽可能持久地运行
and you would want to continue to run the engine off the system any longer than absolutely necessary.
但冷气推进又简单又可靠
But it's simple and reliable,
因为只需打开一个阀门 让高压气体流入发动机
since it's just opening up a valve and letting high pressure gas flow into the engine,
流入预燃室或燃气发生器的涡轮就行了
into the preburner or gas generator through the turbines,
直到泵达到目标转速 开始燃烧
until the pumps are spinning fast enough to begin combustion.
还有些发动机使用称为"启动药盒"的小型发动机来实现类似功能
Some engines will use a tiny little rocket motor called a starting cartridge to do pretty much the same thing.
启动药盒本质上类似小型固推或接触自燃发动机
It's quite literally kind of a small rocket motor of either solid propellant or hypergolic propellants,
用于生成大量燃气 类似气囊里的药盒
that act as a gas generator, almost like the cartridge in an airbag,
核心功能就是瞬间产生大量气体给气囊充气
whose sole purpose is to generate a lot of gas to quickly inflate an airbag.
因此对于需要多次启动的发动机
So for engines that require multiple restarts,
比如需要多次点火才能达到目标轨道的上面级发动机
such as upper stage engines that might have multiple burns to get to their desired destinations
甚至SpaceX的梅林发动机
or even SpaceX's Merlin engine,
需要点火三次——反推 再入 着陆点火 让猎鹰九号火箭着陆
which has to light up three to do that boost back re-entry and landing burn on a Falcon 9,
发动机需要有足够的氮气或氦气或启动药盒
you have to have enough nitrogen or helium or starting cartridges
让这些点火能顺利进行
to get through every single one of those startups.
再额外提一句
We should probably take a quick little second here
还记得火箭实验室电子号火箭上使用电动泵的卢瑟福发动机吧
and mention the Rutherford on Rocket Lab's Electron rocket, that thing's electric pump fed.
我们曾经在《火箭发动机循环方式介绍》视频中提到过
And of course we talked about that in my "How do you power rocket engine" video,
而对于该款发动机的启动来说
but now in context of starting,
大家应该能想象到电动泵火箭的启动有多简单
just think about how much easier it would be to start an electrically pumped feed engine.
只要给泵通电 调整好时序就可以了
You literally just send electricity to pumps and work on the timing,
基本就这些事
and it's pretty much done from there on,
它的时序调校也非常简单
like it'd be so easy to tune,
一切都与发动机速度直接相关 调整好时机即可
and figure out the timing when it's all just direct correlated to the speed of a motor.
可能有人会想能不能用小型电动机来启转 就像汽车发动机那样
Now, it might be tempting to think you could just use a small electric motor
to get these spinning similar to how a car engine starts.
让泵先转起来一会 然后让发动机独立运行
Just get the pump spinning for a brief moment and then let the engine run itself.
但问题是 泵需要相当相当大的功率
The problem is the power requirements for these pumps is insane.
这里并不只是峰值转速
We're not just talking about peak rpm,
我们说的是马力(功率) 即转速与扭矩
we're talking about horsepower, so RPM and torque.
确切地说 是转速乘扭矩
Or more specifically, RPM multiplied by torque.
比如RS-25发动机氢泵的预燃室 平均每公斤输出功率200马力
In fact, the RS-25s fuel preburner delivers about 200 horsepower per kilogram.
你们想象一下200马力的发动机或电动机要多大
Think about that, how big is a 200 horsepower engine or motor?
我估计你几乎找不到能做到1公斤以内的
I'm fairly certain that you won't find one that's only one kilogram.
还有另一种让发动机起转的方法
But there's another way to spin up an engine
不需要额外能量源就能让泵达到目标转速
that doesn't require a separate source to get the pumps up to speed.
称为自身启动 或贮箱压头启动
It's called bootstrapping or tank head or sometimes called deadhead starting,
需要小心缓慢让发动机启转
and it's where you carefully allow the engine to initially light up
只依靠贮箱的压力 和 燃料与发动机的温差的能量
using only the tank pressure and the energy in the thermal difference between the propellant and the engine.
航天飞机与SLS的RS-25发动机使用的就是此方法
The RS-25 on the Space Shuttle and SLS do this.
在最开始涡轮起转时
At the beginning, the turbine will begin to spin up
液氢会流经发动机 内壁 主燃烧室 预燃室
because the hydrogen flowing through the engine, and the walls, and the combustion chamber, and the preburner,
边走边沸腾 像之前提到那样
boils off like we mentioned before.
但我们不把它排出或送入火炬塔
But instead of just having it bleed out and go to the flare stack,
在启动程序中 我们可以让沸腾的高压气氢流过预燃室
during the startup process, we can actually run that high pressure gas through the preburner
驱动涡轮起转
into the turbine to begin spinning it.
然后需要非常精确地控制少量氧进入预燃室 在低压下点燃
Then there's a very delicate and precise dance
to let in some oxygen and light the preburners under low pressures.
这一微弱的燃烧会慢慢积累压力 并在随后几秒内让泵起转
That weak combustion will slowly gain pressure as the pumps begin to spin up over the next few seconds.
随着泵的速度增加 压力增加 导致预燃室的功率增加
As the pumps increase in speed, the pressure rises, which increases the power of the preburner,
进而提高涡轮的转速
which then increases the speed of the turbine,
然后提高泵的转速 然后提高压力
which increases the speed of the pumps, which increases the pressures, yeah.
往复循环下去 直到泵提升到正常燃烧的运转速率
It just keeps going that way and keeps rising until the pumps are at adequate speed for main combustion.
萤火虫太空公司CEO Tom Markusic提到
Fireflie's Tom Markusic mentioned
他们在尝试让Alpha火箭的二级发动机Lightning使用自身启动方法
they're looking into trying to bootstrap their Alpha rocket's second stage engine, the Lightning,
前提是能够移除上面级的氮气起转系统
if at all possible to remove the nitrogen spin start system from the upper stage.
我们在地面上进行氮气起转
We do a nitrogen spin start from the ground.
我们最近进行了一系列测试
Although we've recently did a series of tests
研究起转所需最低转速是多少
where we're trying to figure out how low we can go on that, that spin start.
没错 直到最后能让发动机自身启动
Yeah, before the bootstrap itself.
我们就是在试探发动机顺利起转情况下所需转速的底线
So we've definitely been playing with the level of spin start that's required,
but we do spin start them.
我们发现或许可以在高空只用很少的氮气进行吹转
And, yeah, what we found that we can probably just tickle this thing with a little nitrogen at altitude and
启转所需的转速可以非常……非常低
get it to run much lower... very low spin start requirements.
当然 理想情况是直接压头启动(自身启动)
Yeah, the dream would be to deadhead start it,
但我们暂时还没这么大胆
but we haven't gotten that brave yet.
但自身启动明显是一个反馈环路 需要非常精准的控制才能达速
But bootstrapping is definitely a feedback loop that takes very precise control to get up to speed.
实际上 自身启动难度极大 因为发动机需要经历很长的"瞬态过程"
In fact, bootstrapping is extra difficult because the engine spends a lot of time in what's called a transient,
即发动机从静止到全功率运行的阶段
which is the time between being off and up to full power.
而这个阶段可能是火箭发动机启动中最困难最复杂的部分了
And this is perhaps one of the most complicated and challenging pieces of this puzzle.
瞬态 指两种状态中间的阶段
Transients are the in between moments,
比如发动机从静止到全功率运行 或是相反
so in between the engine being stationary and at full power and vice versa,
甚至节流中的发动机也属于一种瞬态过程
or even between throttle settings, the engine is actually in a transient state,
而当发动机稳定运行时
but once the engine is running and at a steady state,
维持这种运行就相对简单了
it's relatively easy to keep running.
那么瞬态阶段难点在哪?
But why is the transient so hard?
还记得之前提到的鸡生蛋蛋生鸡的情况吧
Well, remember this whole chicken and egg scenario we had.
现在泵的速度起来了
We're just getting the pumps up to speed.
泵由燃气发生器供能 燃气发生器又需要泵提供燃料 那泵要怎样运行?
How do the pumps run if they're powered by a gas generator that itself runs on the pumps?
启动程序中最大的挑战在于
Well, the biggest challenge with the whole startup process
各个组件都是相互关联的
is the fact that everything is intertwined
系统中任何地方的小改变都会瞬间影响其上下游
and a change anywhere in the system
will immediately have an effect upstream and downstream from the change.
我们以RS-25发动机的自身启动为例
So let's say you're trying to bootstrap an engine such as the RS-25.
如前所述 对发动机进行吹除与热环境调控后的第一件事
Like we touched on earlier, the first thing you're going to do after you purge and thermally condition the engine
是要把一部分液氢引入泵与预燃室
is you're going to introduce some liquid hydrogen into the pumps and the preburner.
液氢流经这些地方时会瞬间气化
On its way in, it will flash boil into a gas.
膨胀的氢气开始吹动发动机的涡轮 从而让泵起转
That gas expands and that expanding gas is what's going to start to blow through our turbine,
and get our pumps spinning up.
煽燃太空的CEO Andy Lapsa在访谈中和我解释过此事
Stoke Space CEO, Andy Lapsa, explained this to me
当时我和他站在测试台上 旁边就是他们特牛的自身启动发动机
when I was standing with him on their test stand with their incredible engine that bootstraps.
启动瞬态 有时还有关机瞬态 是火箭发动机上一些风险最高的时刻
The start transient and to some extent also the shutdown transient are
some of the highest risk moments in a rocket engine, right?
你可以想想 像我们这种泵功率一千马力的小发动机
And if you think about it, like our little engine, a thousand HP in the pumps,
大一点的发动机 泵功率可能上万马力了
bigger engines have tens of thousands of HP going through the pumps,
它们从零到全功率运行也就几秒的时间?
and they go from zero to full power in maybe a couple seconds, right?
因此这期间你要控制住每一匹的马力
So you've gotta control all those horses,
保证在瞬态期间一切都正确运行
and make sure they're running in the right direction during that time.
所以 火箭发动机的研发早期通常风险很高
So in early development is usually one of the higher risk activities for rocket engine.
另外多说一句 我真的特别享受这段对话过程
Quick little side note, wow, this is honestly one of my favorite conversations,
Andy Lapsa和他的公司煽燃太空也在制造非常厉害的火箭
and Andy Lapsa and his company, Stoke Aerospace,
is working on an absolutely incredible rocket.
好 至此沸腾后的氢气让涡轮起转 带动了泵的运转
Okay, but that boil off is spinning up the turbine, which spins the pumps,
推进剂的流动开始加快了
so now the propellant is starting to flow a little faster.
只要在启动瞬态期间系统内流体持续向正确方向流动
As long as the pressure in the system continues flowing in this direction during this transient region,
就万事大吉了
you're golden.
但问题是 动作与反应之间通常有些许的延迟
The problem is there's often slight delays between action and reaction.
就好像系统内有一波又一波的压力变化
So it's almost like there's waves of pressure changes moving throughout the system.
如果这样的变化太剧烈
And if those get too extreme,
压力的梯度可能会导致倒流
the pressure gradient might actually start to flow backwards,
导致启动程序停滞 甚至可能炸毁发动机
and you can stall out your startup sequence, or even worse, potentially blow up your engine.
以阀门开度为例
Take a valve opening, for example,
当阀门打开 比如将氧气引入预燃室时
as a valve opens and introduces say the oxygen into the preburners,
同样也会对压力和流量产生影响
that too will have an effect on the pressure and the flow,
然后预燃室的点火也会影响压力和流量
and then the preburner ignition will affect the pressure and the flow.
这些都是往复不断的反馈循环
It's all just a constant back and forth feedback loop.
不过我们刚刚提到了另一话题——点火
But now we've touched upon another piece of the puzzle: ignition.
我们刚刚提到 预燃室会在压力相对较低的情况下点火
We mentioned how the preburner will light under relatively low pressure,
那它究竟是如何点燃的? 什么触发了点火流程?
but how does it actually light, what starts the ignition process?
燃料与氧化剂的混合并不必然导致燃烧反应的发生
Just because you combine your fuel and your oxidizer doesn't mean you're going to get combustion.
实际上 另火箭工程师们失望的是
In fact, most propellants, to the dismay of rocket engineers,
多数推进剂完全可以在同一空间内共存
will kind of happily coexist in the same space and
一些情况下甚至还会完全不经燃烧就一同排放出体系
may even exit the system without unleashing their fiery goodness at all.
更糟心的是 不想让它们点燃的时候 偏偏还可能造成严重的后果
Or even worse, they may accidentally ignite at the wrong time or place, which is often catastrophic.
大家可能听说过"硬启动"这个词
Perhaps you've heard the term hard start.
指的基本就是推进剂以错误配比 在错误时间或错误的地方发生燃烧
This is basically when the propellant combust at the wrong ratios
or perhaps at the wrong time or place.
在最坏的情况 硬启动会让发动机压力严重超限
The worst hard starts can severely over pressure the engine
让涡轮超速 甚至导致猛烈爆炸 完全摧毁发动机
or maybe overspin the turbines or cause an energetic detonation that can completely destroy the engine
甚至还会殃及测试台架 或者与发动机连接的火箭
and sometimes even the test stand and or the rocket that they're actually attached to.
因此 点火的时机与精度至关重要
So the timing and precision of ignition is vital.
大多数火箭发动机都需要一个外部点火源来启动燃烧过程
Like most engines,
rocket engines typically require an external source of ignition to begin the combustion process.
那能不能使用无需点火源的推进剂呢?
But what if we just use propellants that don't need an ignition source at all?
当然可以 接触自燃燃料嘛
Yes, you know, hypergolics,
这一点在我之前每个视频几乎都提到过
we've already touched on them earlier and, and almost every video I've made,
接触自燃是这类燃料最大的优势之一
but being able to spontaneously combust is one of their biggest advantages.
加之这类燃料还不需要额外措施保持低温
And the fact that they don't need any additional considerations to keep liquid at cryogenic temperature,
这都是实打实的优势
is just really a pure bonus.
当然 别误会 它们缺点也很明显 比如剧毒又致癌
I mean, don't get me wrong,
they're a total pain in the butt in other ways like being super toxic and carcinogenic.
但对于点火与可靠性来讲
But in the case of ignition and sheer reliability,
它们简直无敌
they're hard to beat,
因此它们普遍应用在在轨机动推进器和轨道发动机上
which is why they're so common for maneuvering thrusters and on orbit engines
因为它们不会沸腾 对高可靠性需求与长时间的任务很重要
where reliability and long duration missions matter, since they won't boil off.
但对于使用液氧的推进剂
But for LOX based propellants,
如果把燃料和氧化剂简单混合 很可能并不会自发燃烧
if you put your fuel and oxidizer in contact with each other, it likely won't lead to combustion.
如果把液态甲烷和液氧倒进同一个容器中
If you took liquid methane and you poured it into a container of liquid oxygen,
真不太会有什么现象发生
don't really expect anything to happen.
只要没有点火源 哪怕你搅拌几下 两者也会和平共处
Even if you swirled it around without a source of ignition,
the two will coexist surprisingly peacefully.
哪怕两者是气体状态 也是如此
Even in gaseous form, this is true for the most part,
但在气体状态下 一个小小的火苗就很容易点燃
but as a gas, it's much more likely to ignite with just a small ignition source.
因此 非接触自燃燃料与氧化剂不但需要适当混合以稳定燃烧
So non-hypergolic fuels and oxidizers not only need to be properly mixed for stable combustion,
还要为了启动初始燃烧提供一个点火源
they also need an ignition source to initiate the combustion process in the first place.
不过当建立起稳定燃烧后
But once stable combustion has been achieved,
有了足量且稳定的推进剂供应
and assuming there's adequate and stable flow of your propellants,
就不再需要初始的点火程序 发动机可以自持运行了
the initial ignition process is no longer necessary, and it can actually be self-sustaining.
燃烧室内的燃烧本身就是一个持续的点火源
The combustion in the chamber acts as a continual source of ignition.
好 现在我们的目标就是点燃推进剂
Okay, so we've actually got to light up our propellants.
除了接触自燃燃料外 另一个最简单的方法
Perhaps the simplest option outside of hypergolic propellants
可能是苏联在R7火箭上的方案 且至今仍在联盟号上使用
is what the Soviet Union decided to do with the R7 and what Russia still uses today on the Soyuz,
本质就是一个巨型火柴棍
which is basically just some giant matchsticks.
没错 就是在巨型支架上放一组烟火 伸入主燃烧室内
Yep, literally just some large braces with a pair of pyrotechnics that are put inside each combustion chamber
在推进剂到达燃烧室之前点燃
and are all lit prior to the propellants arriving in the combustion chamber.
这种操作能够实现原因是RD-107和RD108发动机的燃气发生器
Now, this is also possible because the gas generator on the RD-107 and RD-108
本质上是一款单组元推进器 不需要额外的点火源
is basically just a monoprop thruster, so it doesn't need a separate source of ignition.
因此整台发动机上唯一要操心的就是主燃烧室的点火
So you could, the main thing you really have to worry about on those engines
is actually igniting the main combustion chamber.
但这种方法有点粗暴 在太空也没什么发挥空间
But it's not very elegant and it's probably not a great option once you're in space either.
因此 我们还需寻求一种适用于在太空的单次或多次点火的方法
So for that, we'll have to look into some other options that are capable of space starts and potentially restarts.
或许最常见的办法是使用"火花塞"
Perhaps one of the most common methods is to basically use a spark plug.
好吧 可能和大家在4S店能买到的那种火花塞不太一样
Okay, maybe not your off the shelf spark plug from a Ford Fiesta,
但概念是相通的
but the concept is the same,
在一个缝隙间施加高电压
take a high electrical voltage and have it jump a gap,
中间电火花的能量刚好可以点燃推进剂
which provides the perfect opportunity to ignite the propellant with ionized electrical energy.
可以想象到
As you can probably imagine,
驱动一台火箭发动机的火花塞需要大量的电能
it does require a good amount of electrical energy to power a rocket engine size spark plug.
所以使用这种方法的发动机可能需要笨重的电池
So rockets using this approach may need to carry heavy batteries,
或者使用地面辅助设备在启动时提供电能
or utilize ground support equipment to run current through the igniter at startup.
另一种方法与电火花启动类似
Another method is similar to a spark igniter,
这种方法类似于汽车工业的柴油发动机
actually, it's again similar to the automobile industry with diesel engines,
即使用辉光塞进行热面点火
and that's using a glow plug.
辉光塞也需要大量电能转化成热量
Glow plugs also require a lot of electricity to convert to heat,
类似于白炽灯泡 电热器线圈或烤面包机
similar to an incandescent light bulb, an electrical heater coil, or a toaster.
辉光塞表面需要有足够的热量
There needs to be enough heat energy on the surface of the glow plug,
才能触发推进剂的燃烧
to initiate combustion of the propellants.
同样 当建立起稳定燃烧后 辉光塞就可以关闭了
And again, once stable combustion has been achieved, the glow plug can just be turned off.
还有一种方法是使用激光
Another method is to use a laser.
激光可以非常精确地聚焦能量束 用来激发推进剂分子
Lasers can very precisely focus the beam of energy and tune it to excite the propellant molecules,
因此它有可能比其他电驱动装置更有效率
so it has the potential to be more efficient than other electrically driven devices.
这种方法目前用得不多
Now, it's not very common yet,
不过空中客车公司的确为自家的一些助推器提供了一些光学点火装置
although Airbus does have some variance of optical ignition for some of their boosters.
以上这些方法都很棒 都有所应用
These methods are all great and commonplace,
但它们都需要大量电能
but they all require massive amounts of electrical power,
而电能通常存储于能量密度不那么高的电池中
which is likely stored in big and not so energy dense batteries.
那么可不可以只使用化学反应的能量来触发点火程序呢?
So what if you actually could just use a chemical reaction to start the ignition process?
其实这种方法也很常见 而且非常有效
This is actually pretty common and extremely effective.
实际上 如果大家看过猎鹰九号或重型猎鹰的发射
In fact, if you've ever seen a Falcon 9 or Heavy launch,
可能曾注意到点火前一瞬间闪过的绿光
you may have noticed a green flash right at the beginning of ignition.
这正是注入的自燃点火剂与氧气接触并开始稳定燃烧的现象
That, my friends, is the injection of a pyrophoric ignition fluid
coming in contact with oxygen to begin stable combustion.
自燃点火剂也是一种自燃燃料
Pyroforks are a type of hypergolic.
这种液体会在接触氧气后瞬间自发燃烧
It's a fluid that will spontaneously and virtually instantaneously react with oxygen.
因此 只要将一些点火剂液体和氧气一起注入燃烧室
So just inject some pyrophoric fluids into the combustion chamber along with oxygen,
就燃起来啦!
and ta-da, you've got yourself a flame.
SpaceX使用一种名为"TEA-TEB"或"三乙基铝三乙基硼"的点火剂
SpaceX uses an ignition fluid called TEA-TEB or triethyl aluminum triethyl borine.
储存在自家火箭上的储罐内 可以让梅林发动机多次重启
It's stored in their own canisters onboard the rocket and allows for multiple restarts of their Merlin engines.
并不是每台发动机都与TEA-TEB储罐相连
Now, not every engine is connected to a TEA-TEB canister,
只有需要重启的发动机才有
only the engines that would do a relight,
即一级九台梅林发动机中的三台 与二级上的真空梅林发动机
so 3 of the 9 Merlin engines on the booster and the vacuum Merlin engine on the upper stage.
但在起飞前 猎鹰九号和重型猎鹰的点火来自地面供应的TEA-TEB
But on the ground, the Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy are lit using ground supplied TEA-TEB,
因为这样就可以把这套系统的重量留在地面
because why not keep those systems and their weight on the ground
不需要把它带上天了
if you don't need to carry that mass off the launch pad?
目前 SpaceX的猛禽发动机使用了多种启动方式
Now, SpaceX has taken a little bit of a hybrid approach to ignition with their new Raptor engine.
猛禽发动机使用的是"火炬点火器"
The Raptor engine uses what are called a torch igniters.
火炬点火器本质上就是点蜡烛用的打火机的高级版本
Torch igniters are basically just a fancy version of the lighters that you might use to light a candle.
不知大家是否听过ASI 全称"增强火花点火器"
You may or may not hear them called ASIs or Augmented Spark Igniters.
ASI自带一个小火花塞
The ASI has its own little small spark ignition
并且有独立的氧气甲烷供应 保证火炬的燃烧
and then its own supply of methylox that allows for the torch to burn.
所以它就像一个由火花塞点着的小型火焰喷射器
So it in itself is almost like a little flame thrower that's initially lit with a spark ignition.
之后这个火炬会在后续点火程序中一直亮着
Then that torch remains lit through the rest of the startup sequence.
有点像固推点火程序中的连锁反应
So it's kind of like the cascading effect of the solid rocket booster ignition,
这里用的是一个小型火花塞点燃一个迷你火焰喷射器
this uses a smaller electrical ignition source to ignite a small baby flame thrower.
但出人意料的是 它只用来点燃猛禽发动机的预燃室
But surprisingly, this is only done on the preburners,
因为实际上 猛禽发动机的主燃烧室内并没有点火装置
because believe it or not, the Raptor engine has no igniters in the main combustion chamber.
这款(一代猛禽发动机)主燃烧室内有火炬点火器
So you got torch igniters for the main chamber,
但在二代猛禽发动机的主燃烧室中就没有火炬点火器了
but Raptor 2 has no torch igniters in the main chamber.
你能看出它的燃烧室外围干净多了
So you can see it's much cleaner around the chamber area.
这怎么……怎么点火的?
How do you... how does it light then?
呃……那就是秘密啦!
Well, that's secret sauce!
虽然伊龙对自家发动机主燃烧室移除点火器的方法讳莫如深
Although Elon was tight-lipped about how exactly they get away with ignition in the main combustion chamber,
但大家认为SpaceX靠的是均质燃烧
it's actually assumed that SpaceX is getting away with homogenous combustion,
也就是说 甲烷和氧气互相接触时基本上是自发燃烧
or basically spontaneous combustion when the methane and oxygen come in contact with each other.
但移除点火器的根本原因是猛禽发动机为全流量分级燃烧循环
But the main reason that they can get away with that is because in the Raptors full flow stage combustion cycle,
所有燃料与氧化剂都流经过各自的预燃室
both the fuel and the oxidizer are preburned in their own preburners,
两者在主燃烧室内相遇时都已是高温燃气
and then they arrive in the main combustion chamber as hot gases already.
这种发生在主燃烧室内高压环境下的气-气反应
So take the fact that it's a gas-gas interaction
along with ridiculously high pressures seen in the combustion chamber,
可能也不需要点火源了
no ignition source is necessary,
推进剂已经足够高温 混合足够均匀 一触即燃
the propellant is already plenty hot and bothered and ready to burn.
到这里 我觉得已经把火箭发动机启动所涉及的内容讲差不多了
Well, I think that pretty much covers all the major parts of starting a rocket engine,
但在我们讲实例之前
but before we get into some examples,
我们先来看看另一个难题——
let's actually cover one more challenge:
在太空启动火箭发动机
starting a rocket engine in space.
在地面上启动火箭发动机就已经很难了
Starting a rocket engine on the ground is pretty challenging,
但地面至少还有些能帮上忙的东西
but at least it has a few things going its way.
首先 火箭发动机可以使用地面支持设备来辅助启动
First off, the rocket can utilize a lot of ground support equipment for startup.
这意味着火箭不需要自带大量用于起转的高压物质
This means the rocket doesn't need to provide crazy amounts of high pressure starting propellant,
还有电能 点火剂 各种所需都可以留在地面
electricity, ignition fluid, or whatever else you may need.
而最大的优势是重力可以让燃料在火箭箱体中沉底
And best of all, gravity is pulling down on the rocket and the propellant held inside.
因此 密度更大的液体燃料会稳稳沉在箱底
So the more dense liquid propellant will sit at the bottom of the tanks,
气体只会出现在箱体顶端 最远离输油管入口的地方
while only at the very top of the tank, opposite of the feed tubes will have gases.
但在太空点燃发动机就没那么简单了
But the same thing isn't true when trying to light an engine in space.
不仅仅是在太空
Well, not just specifically in space,
一切不在地面 不在加速的情况下都是如此
but more when you are not accelerating or not on the ground.
因为当火箭不在加速的时候
Because when not accelerating,
一切物体都在同一个惯性参考系中
everything is in the same inertial reference frame.
换句话说 发动机关机后 航天器漂浮在太空中
In other words, when the engines are off and the spacecraft is just floating in space,
是没有加速度的
there is no acceleration,
推进剂会变成漂浮在箱体内的液球
meaning the propellant is more or less just a blob floating around in a tank.
因此 为了在太空中启动发动机
So in order to start a rocket engine in space,
我们首先要保证液体推进剂在箱中沉底
we first need to make sure the liquid propellant is at the bottom of the tank,
让泵 发动机 或者推进器能顺利吸取到燃料
so the pumps, engine, and or the thrusters can suck up the liquid as intended
而不是吸取到充满气体的气泡 那样情况会很糟
and not get gas bubbles, which can be really bad.
通常的解决办法是使用沉底发动机
A common method for doing this is by using what's known as ullage thrusters.
通常使用小型固推火箭或冷气推进器来让发动机沉底
This is where you either use a small solid rocket motor or cold gas thruster to settle the propellants.
你可以想象自己在用兜网抓蝴蝶
You can almost think of it like a butterfly net trying to catch butterflies.
在太空中一脚加速
By moving through space,
箱底就把液体推进剂全兜住了
it'll basically catch and collect all of the liquid propellant.
我们可以在很多火箭上看到分离时的沉底发动机
You'll see footage of ullage thrusters at stage separation for many rockets.
视频中这个震撼的S-IVB级点火画面实际来自土星IB火箭(二级)
This incredibly iconic imagery of the S-IVB ignition is actually from a Saturn IB,
而它同时也是土星五号火箭的上面级(三级)
but it's the same stage that was used on the upper stage of the Saturn V.
上面的沉底发动机不但可以辅助分离
Not only did the ullage motors help separate the stages,
还起到了燃料沉底的作用
but it also did the propellant settling.
此类操作还适用于太空中发动机的多次启动
This may also need to be done for any restart in space.
比如圆化轨道的点火 或同步转移轨道的点火
Say you have a circularization burn or a geostationary transfer burn,
或者同步轨道直送任务的轨道插入点火 等任何你需要的场合
or a direct to geostationary orbital insertion burn, or whatever you might have.
如果是液体火箭 很可能需要先进行沉底点火
If it's a liquid fueled rocket engine, you'll likely have to do an ullage burn.
就像火箭发动机的泵起转一样
And similar to a rocket needing to do a spin start again,
如果想要进行多次点火
if you need to do multiple burns,
就要有多组固体火箭或使用冷气推进器
you might need to either have multiple solid rocket cartridges or use a cold gas thruster
在需要的时候随时点火
so you can fire it up whenever you need to.
冷气推进器在沉底发动机中很常见
Cold gas is pretty common for ullage thrusters
因为它还可以用于火箭各级的调姿发动机
since it might also be used as maneuvering propellant for stages.
就连猎鹰九号的一级用的也是冷气推进器
Even the Falcon 9 booster has to use cold gas thrusters
让它在反推 再入点火中燃料可以沉底
to settle the propellant before boost back and entry burns.
太空中可以使用冷气推进器 因为推进剂是以高压气体形式储存的
You can use a cold gas thruster in space because it uses gaseous propellant stored at high pressure,
气瓶内压力是均等的 不会有"气泡"这样的东西出现
so there is equal pressure throughout the entire tank, the gases won't blob about.
但有些航天器根本不需要沉底发动机
But some spacecraft don't need ullage thrusters at all.
实际上 许多调姿发动机使用液体双组元推进 通常是接触自燃燃料
In fact, many maneuvering thrusters run on liquid bi-propellants, usually hypergolics,
当它们在太空中需要进行精确机动时
and when they're in space in order to do precise maneuvering,
不可能每次机动前先花时间让燃料沉底
they can't do an ullage burn every single time they need to do a maneuver.
拿SpaceX的龙飞船举例
Take SpaceX's Dragon capsule, for example.
它逐渐接近国际空间站时
As it approaches the International Space Station,
可以看到它的Draco发动机不停在喷喷喷
you'll see it firing its Draco thrusters like crazy.
这些小的脉冲可以让飞船有很高精度的机动控制
These little tiny impulses help precisely control and maneuver the vehicle with extreme accuracy.
Draco发动机使用接触自燃的液体燃料
The Dracos run on hypergolic liquid propellants.
这部分推荐av775116835
那么在燃料箱中有液体的太空中 他们是如何启动这些发动机的?
So how do they fire these engines in space when the tanks have liquids in them?
其实有几种方法实现
There's a few ways to actually do this,
其中最简单的可能是推进剂管理装置 简称PMD
but perhaps the most simple is with a propellant management device or a PMD.
可以是像叶脉或海绵一样的简单装置
This can be a simple device like a vein screen or sponge
利用表面张力和其他一些非常酷的技巧将推进剂导向储箱出口
to wick the propellant towards the tank outlets using surface tension and some other really cool tricks.
还可以在储箱内放置液囊
Another way is with tank bladders.
没错 听上去挺离谱
Yep, believe it or not,
但太空中很多储箱内部还有个液囊 把液体和加压气体分隔开
many in-space tanks will have a bladder inside to separate the liquid from the pressuring gases.
这样 推进剂仍然可以加压到所需压力
This way, the propellants can still be pressurized to necessary pressures,
而液囊还可以防止液体燃料出现气泡
and the bladder will help keep gas bubbles out of the liquid.
它们在球形储箱中非常常见
These are most commonly used on spherical tanks,
不过有些活塞式的储箱也有类似的机构
but there's also some piston tanks that do a similar thing,
但这个操作在细长形状的储箱中更常见 应该可以想象到
but these are more common on elongated cylinders, as you can imagine.
虽说叫活塞 但通常只是一个能动的密封件
Although it is a piston, it's usually just a moving seal.
实际上仍是由氦气加压的
They're still actually pressurized by helium.
多数太空中的推进器与发动机会使用上述几种方法的组合
Most in space thrusters and engines will utilize one or a combination of a few of these devices
来最优化太空中推进剂的使用
to best handle propellants in space.
接下来我还要告诉大家另一种在太空中启动发动机的方法
But what if I told you that there's an even crazier way to light an engine in space
不用沉底发动机 不用储箱液囊 啥都不用!
without ullage thrusters or bladder tanks or anything?
大家有没有注意过联盟号或质子号火箭中间网格连接的部分?
Have you ever noticed the grided fence-looking section of the Soyuz or Proton rockets,
或者大力神2号级间段上开洞的部分?
or maybe you've seen these cutouts on the interstage of the Titan II?
隆重向大家介绍——热分离 也叫热分级
Well, these are necessary to perform the ultimate endearing space events, hot firing, otherwise known as hot staging.
指下面级仍未分离 还在运行时就先点燃上面级的发动机
This is where you light the engines on the upper stage,
while the stage below it is still attached and running.
没错 下面火箭还没烧完的时候 就先把上面的点了
Yep, you just light that engine while there's still a rocket attached to the bottom of it.
字面意思上的"菊花冒火"
This is called "Fire in the Hole" for obvious reasons.
在这样的操作下 推进剂仍在加速中
But by doing this, propellant is already experiencing acceleration.
因此液体会一直乖乖待在箱底
So liquid will obviously be at the bottom of the tanks,
但上面级点火时 尾焰总要有一个出路
but when you light an engine, the exhaust will have to go somewhere,
所以上述这些火箭级间段都有开放的空隙
and now you know why there's so much of an open gap between the stages.
到这里 火箭发动机的启动方式基本就说完了
All right, that pretty much sums up how to start a rocket engine,
接下来找一个现实中的例子 看看大家能不能跟上我的思路
but now let's actually go over a real life example and see if we can follow along.
亲爱的观众朋友们 为了把刚讲的内容攥在一起深入探究
Okay, my friends, I think in order to really put all this together and dive really deep into this,
我决定带大家了解一下火箭发动机启动时的内部
we need to get inside a rocket engine during startup,
一步一步了解这台最复杂的火箭发动机之一的完整启动程序
and go step by step through the entire startup process of one of the most complicated rocket engines,
RS-25发动机
the RS-25.
看完了它的启动程序
If we can walk all the way through this one,
倒不敢说大伙都完全懂了吧
I'm not gonna say that we've mastered it,
但至少也能有个相当不错的理解了
but we should definitely have a very good understanding.
RS-25这款发动机最大的优点是我们对它的启动程序了解得非常深刻
Oh, what's best of all with the RS-25 is we have some incredible insights on how exactly this engine starts up
因为整个启动程序都非常非常详细地公开出来了
because the startup process is actually really, really well publicly documented.
让我们得以非常非常深入地了解在启动程序中发动机内部发生了什么
So we can go really, really deep and actually explain what's going on inside the engine
for the entire startup process.
为此我还买了Robert E. Biggs写的《航天飞机主发动机 最初的十年》
And for this, I actually bought a book called Space Shuttle Main Engine, The First Ten Years by Robert E. Biggs,
这书真的超级牛 把启动程序讲得相当深
and it's an awesome book, it goes really, really in depth into this process.
这本书最牛的是上面这些图表
But the coolest thing about this book is it has these charts
展示了启动程序中压力与阀门状态的变化
showing the pressure and valve openings during the startup process.
我把它简单整理了一下
So we'll draw these out a little bit more cleanly
并在旁边放上发动机的动画
along with a diagram of the engine,
大家可以一步步慢慢看
so we can go just step by step really slowly
了解整个启动程序中的变化
and watch all the things change throughout the entire process.
av300259217
31分钟开始
现在我要再次提醒大家 如果你没看过《火箭发动机循环方式介绍》
Now, I must warn you again, if you haven't watched my "How to power a rocket engine" video,
请务必先去看那期视频 了解富燃闭式循环发动机的原理
you really will need to have a good understanding of the fuel rich closed cycle engine
再回来看这个视频
before you go through this portion of the video.
因为我们将反复深入讲上面的各个部件
Because we get really, really in depth with the exact components.
不过快速复习一下 RS-25发动机有两个预燃室
But as a quick review, the RS-25 has two preburners.
因为发动机是富燃闭式循环 所以两个预燃室都是富燃运行的
Since it's fuel rich closed cycle, both preburners are fuel rich,
所有燃料(氢)都会流经预燃室
meaning all of the fuel will flow through the preburners,
一个预燃室驱动氧泵 另一个驱动氢泵
one preburner powers the oxygen pumps and the other powers the fuel pumps.
氧泵有一个小的二级加压
Then there's a small boost pump on the oxygen side
用于供给两个需要更高压力液氧的预燃室
that feeds the preburners, the higher pressure liquid oxygen that they need to operate,
还有几个阀门
and there's a handful of valves.
预阀用来隔离箱体与发动机
The prevalve that shuts off the tanks to the engines.
然后是氢主阀门 供给两个预燃室与再生冷却通道
Then there's the main fuel valve, which feeds the preburners and the regen cooling channels.
再生冷却系统有一个单独的阀门 称为主燃烧室冷却阀门
But the regen system has a separate valve called the chamber coolant valve,
调整阀门可以控制燃料流向主燃烧室或再生冷却系统
which can be throttled to redirect fuel between the main combustion chamber and the regen system.
然后是三个氧阀 各自负责供给三个燃烧室
Then there's three oxygen valves, one that feeds each of the three combustion chambers,
即两个预燃室和一个主燃烧室
so both of the preburners and the main combustion chamber.
还有一些再循环管路 将沸腾的气态推进剂送回罐体或排放至大气
There's a few recirculation pipes that feed boiling off gaseous propellant
either back into the tanks or vents them out into the atmosphere.
还有增强火花点火器(ASI)
There's also what's called ASIs or Augmented Spark Igniters.
一共有三组ASI 两个预燃室加主燃烧室各一个
There are three sets of ASIs, one in each preburner and one in the main combustion chamber.
这些ASI有自己独立的燃料与氧化剂供应管路
These ASIs have their own fuel and oxygen supply lines
它们是系统中最先接收到燃料的部分
and will be the first items to receive each propellant in the system.
在真实的发动机上显然还有无数其他的小管路和传感器
Now there's obviously a million other small tubes and pipes and sensors littering the real engine,
但为了尽量便于大家理解 我就暂时只展示这么多
but to try to keep this understandable, I think we'll just leave it at this for now.
我们已经知道 低温液体燃料发动机点火前首先要进行吹除与热环境调控
As we know, the first thing a cryogenic liquid propellant engine needs to do
is be purged and thermally conditioned for launch.
对于RS-25来说 最开始这个阶段称为"启动准备阶段"
So the RS-25 first goes into what they call the Start Preparation Phase.
该阶段内 氧侧使用氮气吹除水汽
During this period, the oxygen side of the engine is purged of moisture using nitrogen,
氢侧使用氦气吹除
and the fuel side is purged with helium.
然后发动机内就可以迎接低温推进剂了
Then the engine can have the cryo propellants in its system.
首先打开氢预阀
So they would open the main fuel prevalve
让液氢流经氢泵后来到氢主阀门
that allows liquid hydrogen to flow through the fuel pumps down to the main fuel valve.
有一个小回路 可以排出一部分氢气或泵回燃料入口
There's a small recirculation flow that either dumps some of the hydrogen
or might even pump some of it back into the fuel inlet.
氧侧 打开氧预阀后让氧流入发动机
Liquid oxygen fills the oxygen side of the engine by opening the oxygen prevalve
液氧流经氧泵后会来到三个阀门
and then it flows through the oxygen pumps, up to three valves,
这三个阀门在整个启动程序中都需要精准控制
which will all need to be very precisely controlled during the startup process.
两种推进剂会在发动机内驻留一个多小时 充分调控发动机热环境
The propellants are inside the engine for an hour or more to fully condition the engine.
在整个阶段 主发动机计算机每秒50次不断监测压力和温度
Throughout the stage,
the main engine computer is constantly monitoring the pressures and temperatures
在整个阶段 主发动机计算机每秒50次不断监测压力和温度
50 times per second
确保一切正常
to make sure everything is looking good.
然后 在发动机点火前4分钟
Then at about 4 minutes before engine ignition,
氢主阀门的下游会最后进行一次氦吹除
there's a final engine purge with helium downstream of the main fuel valve.
假如到现在一切正常 所有参数都在预设范围内
Now assuming everything is looking good to go and it's all within the predefined parameters,
计算机会进入"发动机准备完成状态"
the computer will go into what's called the engine ready status.
在发动机点火前3秒
At 3 seconds before engines start,
氢氧两路的泄出阀门关闭
the bleed valves for both the oxygen and hydrogen lines are closed,
发动机等待启动指令
and the engine waits for the start command.
此时发动机已完全进入目标热环境 吹除了大气中的水汽
The engine is now fully thermally conditioned, purged of all moisture from the atmosphere,
准备好迎接即将到来的狂风骤雨 因为……
and ready to take on the challenge of what's to come because …
大的 马上就要来了
here's where things get super complicated.
在发动机收到启动指令后
The moment the start command is received,
第一件事 氢主阀门全开
the first thing that will happen is the main fuel valve is fully opened.
这个阀门最快需要
大约2/3秒达到全开状态
This valve actually takes about two thirds of a second to fully open,
这个阀门最快需要
大约2/3秒达到全开状态
even at its maximum rate.
在氢主阀门打开的同时
At the same time as the main fuel valve is opening,
增强火花点火器(ASI)启动
the ASIs are powered up
准备为到来的所有推进剂点火
and ready to ignite any propellant that they come in contact with.
因此ASI的点火需要先于系统内所有混合推进剂到来之前
So ignition of the ASIs needs to be before any mixed propellants are present in the system.
大家应该能想象到
As you can imagine,
虽然发动机在一般人标准下已经很冷了
despite the engine being cold by human standards,
但氢主阀门下游的部分
the actual components downstream of the main fuel valve
在液氢面前仍然相当"高温"
are still relatively hot, at least compared to the liquid fuel,
因为它们还未像氢主阀门上游
那样填充过低温液体燃料
since they haven't been soaking in that cold cryo liquid propellant,
因为它们还未像氢主阀门上游
那样填充过低温液体燃料
like the parts of the engine that are upstream of the main fuel valve.
发动机的这种温差足以让涡轮起转
This energy from the latent heat of the engine
is enough to begin spinning the turbine.
发动机启动初始阶段
起转的部分类似于膨胀循环发动机
The engine initially is starting up and beginning to spin up
发动机启动初始阶段
起转的部分类似于膨胀循环发动机
as an expander cycle engine,
即之前提到的"自身启动"或"压头启动"
otherwise known as bootstrapping
or deadhead starting like we mentioned before.
但系统正面临着相当大的热力学不稳定因素
But it's facing some pretty major thermodynamic instability.
燃料的瞬间沸腾
As the propellant flash boils,
会带来不可控但可预测的振荡
it'll create uncontrollable but predictable oscillations,
而这就是最难的部分
and that's one of the hardest things here.
因为一切反应都会有些许延迟
Since everything has a little bit of a delayed reaction,
你需要预测在实际过程中
何时会出现压力的波峰与波谷
you need to actually predict
你需要预测在实际过程中
何时会出现压力的波峰与波谷
when the peaks and dips and the pressure will occur
你需要预测在实际过程中
何时会出现压力的波峰与波谷
during this process.
振荡过程会持续大约1.5秒
These oscillations will occur for about 1.5 seconds
直到主燃烧室来到平衡点(prime)
until the main combustion chamber reaches what's known as prime.
当前情况的平衡点
指两侧喷注器压力稳定
Now prime in this example is when the pressure is stable
当前情况的平衡点
指两侧喷注器压力稳定
on each side of the injector,
特指质量流速稳定
well, specifically when the mass flow rate is stable.
因此 当泵与燃烧室之间有稳定流量时 三个燃烧室就都到平衡点了
So prime occurs in all three combustion chambers
when there's stable flow between the pumps and the chambers,
每个燃烧室的来到平衡点的时间非常重要
each combustion chamber's targeted prime time is very important
这样才能让一切物质向着正确方向流动
so as to keep things moving in the right direction.
现在 氢已进入系统中 开始流经泵和涡轮
So we've introduced fuel into the system and mostly flowing through the pumps and the turbines
并开始让发动机起转了
and beginning to get the engine spinning.
氢还流经了三个有供电的火花点火器
Fuel is flowing through the three sparking igniters and they have electrical power.
现在我们该开始充填氧化剂了
Now we've got to start introducing oxygen.
最先接收氧的是氢预燃室内的点火器
The first thing that's going to receive oxygen is the igniter inside the fuel preburner.
基本上只要氢预燃室氧阀开始打开
系统内的液氧就会开始流动
The system will start to flow liquid oxygen
基本上只要氢预燃室氧阀开始打开
系统内的液氧就会开始流动
basically as soon as that fuel preburner LOX valve
基本上只要氢预燃室氧阀开始打开
系统内的液氧就会开始流动
starts to even open.
氢预燃室氧阀只要打开5%
At just 5% opening of the fuel preburner oxygen valve,
液氧就能供给到点火器
LOX is directed straight to the igniter.
阀门开始打开的时间
和氧气开始流入点火器的时间
The timing of when the valve starts to open
阀门开始打开的时间
和氧气开始流入点火器的时间
and when the oxygen will start flowing into the igniter
与振荡期间压力的第一次下降完全吻合
coincides perfectly with the first dip in pressure
during those pressure oscillations.
保证氢不会倒流进入氧侧系统
This helps make sure that you don't have backflow of hydrogen
up through the oxygen system,
还能保证首段燃烧有正确的混合比
but also ensures that you're setting up to have the right mixture ratio
for the first bit of combustion.
从这时开始
氢预燃室氧阀需要不断调整
From here, the fuel preburner oxygen valve has to do a lot of work
来"弹反"系统内振荡
带来的压力高低变化的冲击
to kind of ride the waves of those oscillations
来"弹反"系统内振荡
带来的压力高低变化的冲击
to flow through the highs and the lows of the system,
而且还不能盯着压力的变化调整阀门开度
and again, they can't react to the pressure oscillations
因为阀门开度和下游变化之间会有延迟
because of the delayed reaction between the valve opening
and the events happening downstream.
所以振荡的情况必须提前精确记录 用于实际中的预测
So these oscillations had to be precisely documented and predicted.
实际上 图表中绿线的每一次开度变化
In fact, every time you see the valve moving during this period,
大家应该都能想象到
研发幕后炸了多少发动机
you can pretty much assume that
大家应该都能想象到
研发幕后炸了多少发动机
there was an engine that blew up
炸完后 上上下下又修改了多少次
and changes had to be made from the lessons learned.
此时 泵的转速已经很高了
By this point, the pumps are spinning pretty quick,
系统中三个燃烧室也开始接近平衡点
and the system is getting closer to reaching an equilibrium in all three chambers, or again, hitting prime.
在1.25秒
At 1.25 seconds,
发动机会对氢泵涡轮转速自检
it'll do a speed check of the fuel pump turbine.
工程师发现 泵转速要达到4600RPM
It was found that the pump needed to be above 4,600 RPM
才能进行后续氢预燃室和主燃烧室的点火
in order to continue moving forward
into fuel preburner and main combustion chamber ignition.
否则氢燃气压力无法顶住
主燃烧室的压力
Otherwise, there wouldn't be enough hydrogen pressure
否则氢燃气压力无法顶住
主燃烧室的压力
to overcome the main combustion chamber pressure.
在1.4秒 氢预燃室达到平衡点
At 1.4 seconds, the fuel preburner hits prime
此时压力会有一个骤降后陡增的过程
right when there's that large dip in pressure,
and then that causes a rapid rise in pressure.
这会导致氢涡轮转速的陡增
Now, this causes the fuel turbine to spin up very quickly.
实际上 此时氢涡轮后
主燃烧室那边并没有背压
In fact, there's virtually no back pressure after the turbine
实际上 此时氢涡轮后
主燃烧室那边并没有背压
from the main combustion chamber yet,
因为主燃烧室此时尚未达到平衡点
since that hasn't hit prime at this point.
因此 涡轮的转速会急剧提升
So the turbine spins up ridiculously fast.
如果不加干预 涡轮最终会超速
If left unattended, it would actually overspeed the turbine
甚至造成灾难性的后果
and would likely cause a catastrophic failure.
因此 主燃烧室到达
平衡点的时间极其重要
So making sure the combustion chamber hits prime
因此 主燃烧室到达
平衡点的时间极其重要
at exactly the right moment is extremely important,
这样才能及时提供足够背压
to provide the necessary back pressure,
防止涡轮转速提升不会太快
so the turbine doesn't spin up too fast.
注意到 整个流程要先起转氢侧的涡轮和泵
Now notice we are spinning up the fuel turbine and pumps first.
这样保证了整个体系内氢的压力更高
This ensures that the whole system has higher fuel pressure,
启动时还能有一个低温 富燃混合的环境
and ratios that will ensure a cool fuel rich start.
虽说氢也不能太多 不然就点不着了
Obviously, it can't be so fuel rich that it floods a system and can't be lit,
但富燃总好过配比接近理想化学比而烧毁
but it's better to stay too rich rather than to lean and be anywhere closer to stoichiometric.
现在 我们回到发动机点火程序开始后0.2秒
So let's actually walk backwards now a bit to 0.2 seconds after engines start,
此时 氧主阀门开始打开
that's when the main combustion chambers
oxygen valve will start to open
让氧流入主燃烧室点火器
to flow oxygen into the main combustion chamber igniter.
氧主阀门缓慢打开至60%
The main combustion chamber valve
is slowly open to just under 60% open.
这个缓慢的操作 外加系统的延迟
The delay and the slow rate of opening
让主燃烧室点火器
在发动机启动0.85秒后获取氧供应
makes it so the main combustion chamber igniter
让主燃烧室点火器
在发动机启动0.85秒后获取氧供应
has oxygen at 0.85 seconds after engine start,
并且让主燃烧室点火器以富燃配比开始工作
and this will begin the main combustion chamber ignition at a nice safe fuel rich mixture ratio.
主燃烧室在1.5秒达到平衡点
Main combustion chamber hits prime at 1.5 seconds,
让主燃烧室内压强迅速提升
which causes the pressure
in the main combustion chamber to rise rapidly
提供背压 为氢涡轮提供阻力
防止转速超限
and helps prevent over speeding the fuel turbine
提供背压 为氢涡轮提供阻力
防止转速超限
with an increase in back pressure
提供背压 为氢涡轮提供阻力
防止转速超限
and therefore resistance on the turbine.
好 我们再把时间往回拨 看看氧预燃室系统
Okay, so let's actually go backwards again in time
and go through the oxygen preburner system.
发动机启动程序开始后0.12秒
氧预燃室氧阀开始打开
The oxygen preburner valve initial opening is just
发动机启动程序开始后0.12秒
氧预燃室氧阀开始打开
0.12 seconds after engines start,
设计上 阀门开启时
就能为氧预燃室点火器供氧
but it's designed in a way that its initial opening
设计上 阀门开启时
就能为氧预燃室点火器供氧
is all it takes to power the oxygen preburner igniter.
这样的时序控制
让氧预燃室点火器在0.95秒点火
The timing of this makes it so the oxygen preburner igniter
这样的时序控制
让氧预燃室点火器在0.95秒点火
is lit at 0.95 seconds,
比主燃烧室点火器的点火晚0.1秒
just 1/10 of a second after the main combustion chamber igniter.
氧预燃室氧阀设计上
在46%开度之前流量很小
Now, the oxygen preburner valve
氧预燃室氧阀设计上
在46%开度之前流量很小
is designed to not really flow oxygen
氧预燃室氧阀设计上
在46%开度之前流量很小
all the way through until about 46% open.
因为保守控制氧流量是非常重要的
Again, it's very important
that the flow of oxygen is generally conservative.
需要非常小心调整
既要让体系有足够氧发生燃烧
It's a careful balance
需要非常小心调整
既要让体系有足够氧发生燃烧
between giving the system enough oxygen to begin combustion,
从而提供足够运转发动机的功率
and help to provide the power necessary to run the engine,
还不能让氧多到影响发动机燃烧配比
导致温度过高
but not giving it too much oxygen
还不能让氧多到影响发动机燃烧配比
导致温度过高
where the engine can start to run lean
还不能让氧多到影响发动机燃烧配比
导致温度过高
and experience damaging temperatures.
大家应该可以看出 氧预燃室氧阀可以控制氧预燃室的功率
As you can imagine, the oxygen preburner valve helps control the power of the oxygen preburner,
从而调控氧泵的涡轮转速
which controls the speed of the oxygen pumps turbine,
进而控制氧泵转速
which is what controls the speed of the oxygen pumps,
因而控制氧侧系统的压力
which is what controls the pressure in the oxygen system.
这一个阀门对整个发动机影响巨大
So that one valve actually has a huge effect on the entire engine.
氧预燃室在1.6秒达到平衡点
是三个燃烧室中最晚的
The oxygen preburner is the last of the three chambers
氧预燃室在1.6秒达到平衡点
是三个燃烧室中最晚的
to hit prime at 1.6 seconds,
同样 还是为了保证体系内
氧压力不会过高
and that's again done to ensure the oxygen pressure
同样 还是为了保证体系内
氧压力不会过高
doesn't get too high in the system.
在发动机启动程序开始后1.7秒
At 1.7 seconds after engines start,
发动机主计算机证实三个燃烧室点火正常
the main engine computer verifies that all three combustion chambers had proper ignition
运转正常
and are operating normally.
在发动机三个燃烧室点火
并来到平衡点这个阶段开始时
At the beginning of this phase,
where the engine has all three combustion chambers lit and primed,
主燃烧室处在
大约25%的功率运行状态
the main combustion chamber is at
roughly 25% of its rated power level,
但这还很不稳定
but it's far from stable.
如果大家看过这段时间的慢放视频
And if you check out slowmo footage around this time,
会发现发动机的喷管此时正在疯狂抖动
you'll actually notice the rocket engine's nozzle just oscillating like crazy.
还会注意到一些气流尖峰沿喷管内壁上行
You might also notice there's some big spikes of flow separation going up into the nozzle,
因为此时喷管内的压力实际上低于海平面压强
and that's because the pressure inside the nozzle is actually still lower than atmospheric pressure at sea level.
所以大气中的空气会沿着喷管内壁"爬行"上去
So the air's atmosphere is actually kind of creeping back up into the nozzle,
这些激波形成时会产生振荡
and it has these big oscillations as those shockwaves kind of form,
并且此时是有些不稳定的
and it has a bit of an instability at this point.
因此 为了提高稳定性和压力 增加安全裕度
So in order to increase stability and pressure and increase safety margin,
之前完全打开的主燃烧室冷却阀门
the chamber coolant valve,
which was fully open up until this point
节流至70%
is throttled down to 70%.
让更多的氢流入主燃烧室
This forces more fuel into the main combustion chamber.
这一过程持续0.4秒
It does this for 0.4 seconds
来辅助吸收压力与温度的振荡
to help absorb variations in the pressures and temperatures.
到这个时刻 发动机主计算机一直处在开环工作模式
Now, up until this point, the main engine computer's actually been operating in open loop control,
即发动机只被动接收预编程的指令
meaning it's only receiving pre-programmed commands,
没有数据的互动 只执行指令
it's not like reacting to anything, it's just a set of orders basically.
但在发动机启动程序开始2.4秒后
But at 2.4 seconds after engines start,
计算机进入主燃烧室压力
(氧预燃室氧阀)闭环控制
the computer goes into a closed loop control,
意味着之后发动机功率
稳步提升的过程中
meaning that throughout the rest of the ramp
意味着之后发动机功率
稳步提升的过程中
up to rated power level,
发动机主计算机
开始对压力温度数值做出反应
the main engine computer is actually reacting
发动机主计算机
开始对压力温度数值做出反应
to the pressures and temperatures,
作出相应调整 让数值稳定提升
and making adjustments accordingly
to try and follow the path to ramp up.
这一步主要靠调整氧预燃室氧阀
Most of this is done by controlling the oxygen preburner oxygen valve,
因为刚刚提到 这个阀门可以对很多地方产生影响
because like we said, that really has a huge effect on everything else.
但不要以为这很简单
But remember, again, this is all pretty tricky
因为读取主燃烧室温度
并做出反应是有很大延迟的
since there's a pretty big delay
因为读取主燃烧室温度
并做出反应是有很大延迟的
between reading the combustion chamber temperatures
因为读取主燃烧室温度
并做出反应是有很大延迟的
and reacting to it.
而且这并不是"反应时间"
It's not actually like the reaction time,
而是比如阀门打开后
影响到下游这一物理过程的延迟
but just how long it physically takes to say open a valve
而是比如阀门打开后
影响到下游这一物理过程的延迟
and for those changes to make a difference downstream.
因此这一切都需要非常小心
So this all has to be done just incredibly carefully.
在3.8秒 启动混合比
(氢预燃室氧阀)闭环控制
At 3.8 seconds, the system goes into
在3.8秒 启动混合比
(氢预燃室氧阀)闭环控制
fully closed loop mixture control.
也就是说 此时不但主燃烧室压力
(氧预燃室氧阀)是闭环控制的
So not just closed loop has it had been operating,
混合比(氢预燃室氧阀)
也加入了闭环控制
but now it's fixed even with its mixture ratio,
也就是说 通过调控氢预燃室氧阀
meaning only the fuel preburner oxygen valve is used
维持主燃烧室内正常的混合比
to ramp up the correct mixture ratio
in the main combustion chamber,
液氧:液氢=6:1
trying to get to that 6:1 ratio,
此时大约是启动指令发出后5秒
which will occur right around 5 seconds.
也意味着发动机来到了
全功率运行状态
And this also means the engine has fully reached
也意味着发动机来到了
全功率运行状态
operating power levels.
在数值上升过程中 我们终于看到了那迷人的马赫环 或叫钻石激波
And during this ramp up period we're awarded with those gorgeous shock diamonds or mach diamonds,
RS-25上的马赫环真的太好看了
and they're just so perfect on the RS-25.
上述这些 通通发生在短短几秒内 我觉得太牛了
It's honestly crazy to me that this all happens in such a short period of time
而且还可以做到在航天飞机和现在SLS上那样的可靠性
and that they could ever achieve the reliability they did with a Space Shuttle and now with SLS.
我们现在回头再看一遍这个图表
And now let's take a look back at the chart again one more time,
希望大家对发生了什么
已经有了些许的理解
now that we hopefully understand a little bit of
希望大家对发生了
什么已经有了些许的理解
what's actually going on.
我们能看出压力值的振荡
与对应阀门的开闭
We can see how each of those dips of pressure
我们能看出压力值的振荡
与对应阀门的开闭
and the corresponding valve positions
背后是多少测试与教训
was obviously a learning lesson.
RS-25在23周内测试了19次
There were 19 tests through 23 weeks
更换了8次涡轮泵
with 8 turbo pump replacements
一切只为搞定前两秒的启动程序
just to get through the first 2 seconds of startup.
然后在12周内又进行了18次测试
And it took another 18 tests, 12 weeks,
更换5次涡轮泵
and 5 more turbo pump replacements
只为达到全推力运行
just to get up to full power.
说实话我甚至以为会炸得更多
That's honestly actually fewer bits of hardware
than I would've guessed,
但也能让大家了解火箭发动机的研发
有多么困难多么烧钱
but it still helps appreciate
但也能让大家了解火箭发动机的研发
有多么困难多么烧钱
how hard and how expensive engine development can be.
我并没有说开发出可靠的启动程序后 就什么经验教训都不需要了
Not to say there weren't additional lessons to be learned once they developed a reliable startup sequence,
但在稳定状态下运转比动态的启动程序要容易得多
but operating at a steady state is orders of magnitude easier than the dynamic startup process.
我想这个例子我已经讲得差不多了
Well, I think that should do it for an example,
因为 我真的只能讲这么深了
I mean, that's about as deep as I can get,
我觉得我们可以开始了解一下发动机的节流
so I think it's time we wrap up by touching on throttling
还有与启动程序相反的关机程序
and the opposite of startup shutting the engine down,
并在最后进行一些思考与总结
and then we'll do some final thoughts and a summary.
当然了 启动并不是火箭发动机唯一要面对的动态过程
Of course, startup isn't the only dynamic situation a rocket engine faces.
诚然 发动机运行起来
Sure, once an engine running,
状态就稳定多了 不太会有什么以外情况
it's in a steady state, and there shouldn't really be any real surprises.
但当发动机在最大动压处收油门
But what happens when an engine throttles down for maximum aerodynamic pressure or MaxQ,
维持峰值加速度 甚至着陆回收时又发生了什么呢?
maintaining desired peak G loads or even when it's landing?
相信大家也能想象到 不同发动机肯定各不相同
As you can likely imagine, this varies very much from engine to engine,
而且说实话 这些都够再做一期视频了
and frankly, this is probably a topic for another video.
不过简言之 火箭发动机通常靠减少预燃室或燃气发生器的流量实现节流
But in short, engines generally throttle by reducing the flow to the preburner or the gas generator,
因此 通常只靠一个阀门 一般是减少氧的供应
so usually with one of the control valves and often by reducing the flow of oxygen
来维持发动机的富燃状态
to maintain a fuel rich state.
发动机的关机也是类似的情况
The same thing goes for shutting an engine down.
这是另一个动态过程
It's another dynamic event,
基本规则就是永远不要让发动机跑到理想化学比燃烧
and the general rule of thumb is you never want to get close to stoichiometric conditions.
因为发动机通常是处在富燃状态的
Since engines usually run fuel rich,
所以先减少氧气供应 再降低燃料供应
you do this by first reducing the oxygen flow and then the fuel flow.
一般来说 发动机的关机过程越快越好
Generally, you want to shut an engine down pretty much as quickly as possible,
但这个速度经常会有一个限制 避免过高的过载
but you often have limits on how quickly you can do that to avoid high G loads.
比如对于航天飞机上的RS-25发动机
For example, when the RS-25 was on the Space Shuttle,
就有一个推力衰减速率的限制
there was a limit to how quickly the thrust could decay,
防止过载超出轨道器的结构限制
so as not to exceed the orbiter's structural limit.
氧预燃室氧阀的初始移动限制为每秒45%
The initial oxygen preburner oxygen valve motion was limited to 45% per second.
氧主阀门也有一个特定的关闭速率
The main oxygen valve also had to be closed at a particular rate,
但这主要是为了确保涡轮上有足够的背压
but mostly to ensure there was sufficient back pressure on the turbines,
保证涡轮在关闭过程中不会意外超速
so they wouldn't accidentally over speed during the shutdown process.
对我来说 要考虑到每一个输入和条件等因素 想想都太恐怖了
To me, it's just crazy how many considerations there are to absolutely every single input and condition.
我觉得这当中有无数要学习的
Like I feel like there's a million lessons to be learned that
而且说实话 很多时候只能靠一次次炸毁发动机
frankly can really only be learned the hard way by examining scraps of an engine
才能发现问题 积累经验
and trying to figure out what went wrong.
我觉得正是这样的想法 才驱动SpaceX不停地测试他们的猛禽发动机
I think it's kind of this mindset that drives SpaceX to test their Raptor engines so quickly.
他们深知 只有让发动机在试车台上受尽折磨
They truly believe that by just getting them out on the stand,
而不是像供一尊佛一样摆在那供着
not treating them as some one-off golden pony or something,
才能真正学到东西
they can learn more quickly.
他们也从中吸取了无数教训
There's countless lessons that they have learned,
让猛禽发动机现在终于能够安全启停
that have shaped safe operation during startup throttling and shut down.
我相信很多人很想知道猛禽发动机具体是如何启动的
And I know that many of you are probably wanting to know how exactly the Raptor engine starts.
它的启动程序并不像RS-25发动机那样完善地公开过
Its startup process isn't as well publicly documented, of course, as say the RS-25,
但也的确是有一些相似的
but it does have some similarities.
显然 猛禽像RS-25一样有两个预燃室
It of course, has two preburners, like the RS-25,
但最大的不同在于 猛禽的预燃室一个富燃一个富氧
but the biggest difference is that one preburner is fuel rich and the other is oxidizer rich.
因此这两个预燃室之间交输的耦合程度更高
So this means the interaction between the two preburners is even more intertwined.
其中一个速度的改变会迅速对另一侧产生直接影响
Changing the speed of one has a very direct correlation and impact on the other one.
powerhead/powerpack 动力头/动力包
指涡轮泵与预燃室及其附属设备的总成
国内一般叫"半系统"
猛禽发动机有一套液氧的动力头和一套燃料的动力头
In the case of Raptor, you've got an oxygen power head and a fuel power head,
它们使用不同的轮轴 对应两套涡轮与预燃室
and they're different shafts and you've got two turbines and two preburners.
两者互相还有燃气的交输
And they're cross feeding one another.
因此 相比梅林发动机 猛禽发动机的启动程序极其复杂
So the start sequence for Raptor is insanely complicated
compared to the start sequence for Merlin.
一切都要完美精准控制 因为互相之间都有依赖——
It has to be perfectly precise cause each one relies -
这一切就好像是在燃料和液氧动力头之间的刀尖上跳舞一样
Basically you're doing this delicate dance
between the fuel power head and the oxygen power head,
两者一旦同步出问题
and if they get out of sync,
正常是极度富氧/富燃状态的
预燃室可能就跑到理想燃烧比 直接被烧穿或炸烂了
then you can go stoichiometric in the preburners and melt or explode the preburners.
等它运行起来 情况就简单多了
Once it's running, it's a much easier situation.
但启动程序有任何出错 发动机就可能会熔化或炸毁
But if you get anything wrong with that star sequence you're either gonna melt or explode the engine.
猛禽发动机的起转使用的氦或氮
Initial spin up of Raptor is done with either helium or nitrogen.
而之前我们也提到 预燃室内使用火炬点火器
And as we mentioned before, there are torch igniters in the preburners,
主燃烧室内可能还有类似均质燃烧的点火方式
and likely some kind of homogenous ignition in the main combustion chamber.
但之后 我真的很难想象启动程序中发动机内部到底发生了什么
And from there on, I honestly can't even begin to imagine
what goes on internally to balance the startup process.
也难怪他们为此每天要点火大约五次猛禽发动机
It's no wonder they're firing up raptors about five times every day at this point.
他们必须解决所有难题
They've really gotta get all the kinks worked out
才能让这么多台猛禽发动机同时点火
because there's going to be so many engines going through startups simultaneously,
不容半点差池
it has to be perfect.
总结下来 火箭发动机的启动非常困难
So to summarize, starting a rocket engine is very hard.
有些稍微简单
Some are easier than others,
大家可以想象 为什么公司弄出火箭发动机或概念的PPT很容易
but you can imagine why it's easy for a company to come up with a rocket engine or concept
但真走到生产与运行那步却难如登天
and very hard for them to get into production and operation.
因此 每当有航天机构分享他们的发动机成功点火试车
So when a company shares that they've successfully started up an engine
并在功率上成功达到运行指标
and made it all the way up into operating power levels,
真的值得鼓掌 因为他们可能已经跨过研发中最大的坎
it's very applause worthy as they've likely made it through the biggest hurdles in development.
而且了解到不同发动机的启动程序
And it's really fun to see how different programs tackle starting an engine,
以及为了让发动机更可靠而采用的技术 真的很有意思
and what techniques they might employ to achieve a reliable engine.
当然 火箭发动机的启动也可以复杂到
But of course, starting a rocket engine can be extremely complicated,
在几毫秒内控制阀门开闭仅仅两度
like having valves changing their position
by just two degrees within a few milliseconds
以避免像RS-25那样
压力振荡造成灾难性的情况
to avoid catastrophic conditions
from pressure oscillations like in the RS-25.
掌握这样的启动程序
要花费数千小时的研发
Mastering this sequence can take thousands of hours of development,
消耗上百万美元硬件与时间
which means millions of dollars in time and hardware,
背后需要无数人刻苦攻关与排故
which can mean years and years of hard work and troubleshooting.
人类能制造出如此复杂又可靠的火箭发动机 简直就是奇迹
It is pretty much a miracle to me that people have figured out
how to make rocket engines that are so complicated and so reliable,
尤其考虑到启动过程中发动机离爆炸只有一步之遥
considering how close to catastrophe they are throughout the entire startup sequence.
基本就是这样了
But that pretty much does it.
希望本期视频能让大家了解到工程师与科学家都要解决哪些难题
Hopefully this video helps give you an appreciation of what engineers and scientists have to solve
才能让你我热爱的火箭刺破苍穹
before your favorite rocket has ever made it to the launchpad for the first time.
这背后的庞大工程想想都让人头皮发麻
It's just absolutely incredible how much work has to go into this.
如果大家有其它问题或想法 欢迎在下方评论区分享
Let me know if you have any other questions or thoughts in the comments below.
非常感谢在Patreon上赞助我制作像这样的视频的大家
I owe a huge thank you to my Patreon supporters for helping make videos like this,
让本频道所做的一切成为可能
and everything we do here at Everyday Astronaut possible.
我还要额外鸣谢我们的任务组长与负责人
I also have to give a little extra thank you to our Mission Directors and Commanders
他们为视频的脚本做出了贡献
who were there for some of the script read throughs.
我做了两套脚本 在Discord上通读过一遍
We did two of them for this script where I'm sitting there reading through the entire thing in Discord
而大家给我评价与反馈
and people are giving me comments and feedback as we read.
字斟句酌
We kinda go like paragraph by paragraph.
通读几次后脚本也进步了很多
We developed that script a lot just from those read throughs.
并且组内其他任务专家与飞行员们
And then, the rest of our Mission Specialists and Pilots
最后也都自行通读了一遍脚本 并提出了很多宝贵意见
ended up doing a script read through on their own and giving a lot of good feedback
对本期视频有很大的帮助
and this video has really evolved a lot.
我从中也学到了无数东西
And I learned a ton making this,
对我来说 这一直是我判断一个视频质量的标志
which to me is always kind of the bookmark on whether or not I think a video is going to be good.
基本就是看我学到了多少东西 而我这次学到太多太多了
It's just based on how much did I learn and I learned so much.
也真心希望大家也能有所收获
So I really hope you guys do too.
因此 如果你也想提供你的反馈 并参与这些视频的制作
So if you want to help give your feedback and be involved in the making of these videos
或者你只是想提供些经济上的支持
or if you just want to help financially support,
欢迎前往下方链接赞助我
head on over to patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
网上冲浪的时候也可以看看网店里这些时髦的衬衫
And while you're online, be sure and check out our awesome merch store for shirts like this,
比如这件《日心》衬衫
the Heliocentric Shirt,
这实际上是《天天太空人》发行的一张EP的专辑封面
this is actually based on the album art from an EP I released as Everyday Astronaut.
可以在Spotify和Apple Music上听到 曲名就叫《日心》
You can find it on Apple Music and Spotify, etc, etc, called Heliocentric.
也别忘了看看我们网店的新东西
But also be sure and shop around and check out all of our new cool stuff,
比如这款超高细节的1:100猎鹰九号火箭模型
including our super highly detailed 1:100 scale metal Falcon 9 model rockets
目前有货
while we have them in stock.
还有新款的全流量分级燃烧循环图案的衬衫
Or check out our new Full Flow Stage Combustion Cycle Shirt,
或者其他服饰 比如未来火星主题帽衫和航天飞机弹射服主题帽衫
or awesome dress wear, our Future Martian collection, our Space Shuttle Ejection Suit Hoodie,
还有给未来航天爱好者的童装
cute clothes for your little space cadets,
等等各种有趣商品 都在下方链接中
and all sorts of other fun stuff at everydayastronaut.com/shop.
感谢大家 就到这里了
Thanks everybody. That's gonna do it for me.
我是《天天太空人》的Tim Dodd
I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut,
把航天知识带给寻常百姓家~
bringing space down to earth for everyday people.